<skill name="skill-writing" v="1">
<desc>Creating and refining skills - extracting patterns from practice into portable, reusable knowledge.</desc>

<overview>
Skills are teachable processes. They capture how to do something so agents can learn it. The goal is portable, dense, useful knowledge - not documentation or ceremony.

See `llxml-writing.xml` for format/spec details. This skill covers the craft.
</overview>

<when_to_create>
- A pattern has emerged from actual practice (not theory)
- You've done the thing multiple times and it's stabilized
- The knowledge would help future agents or sessions
- It's distinct enough to stand alone (not just part of another skill)

Not: when you think something *should* exist, or to feel organized.
</when_to_create>

<extraction>
<from_practice>
Observe what you actually do, then codify it. Not the other way around.

Bad: "A retro should have these sections because that's proper."
Good: "I notice when there's a bug fix, I always add a 'what was learned' section."

The pattern comes first. The skill captures it.
</from_practice>

<conditional_sections>
Some things only apply sometimes. Don't make them boilerplate.

Example: "What Was Learned" only appears when there was a problem that got fixed. It earns its place - don't add it to feel thorough.

Mark conditional sections as conditional. Future readers need to know when to include them.
</conditional_sections>
</extraction>

<quality>
<density>
Skills should be tight. Say more with less. If you can cut 60% and lose nothing, do it.

Audit after writing: what's filler? What's ceremony? What's actually load-bearing?
</density>

<portability>
Skills get shared, vendored, read by different agents in different contexts.

- No poisonous language (profanity, negativity, blame)
- No hardcoded paths or machine-specific details
- Neutral, direct tone
- Self-contained (don't assume context)
</portability>

<audit_your_work>
After writing, read it fresh. Ask:
- Did I write from theory or practice?
- Is anything here just because it "should" be?
- Would this help someone who's never seen it before?
- Is there language that shouldn't ship?
</audit_your_work>
</quality>

<evolution>
Skills aren't permanent. They evolve through use.

- Bump version when changes are significant
- Compress when bloated
- Split when doing too much
- Merge when overlap is obvious
- Delete when obsolete

A skill that never changes probably isn't being used.
</evolution>
</skill>
